Guide to the Spanish Advertising Broadsides (Auca and Alelujas), 1938-1985 and undated RL.11006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Spanish Advertising broadsides (Auca and Alelujas)
1938-1985 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
RL.11006
3 Linear Feet
An auca is a graphic format popular in Spain and especially in the region of Catalonia around Barcelona. The genre dates at least to the 17th century but was banned during the 18th century before experiencing a renewal during the 19th and later the 20th centuries as a uniquely Catalonian form of expression. It takes the form of a cartoon or a comic strip, typically with 48 blocks of image and text, although some may have less. An auca is generally produced as a single sheet, but occasionally a booklet form is used. The captions tend to have some sort of consistent rhyme to assist with the flow and storytelling. Many times the term “auca” appears in the title, but another term, “aleluya,” is used, apparently interchangeably. Some sources indicate that the aleluya originated in Castile and originally included religious elements that were shed over time. The aucas found in this collection are focused primarily on advertising a range of products, businesses, services or entertainments such as films, but also present are public service announcements for topics such as safety, health or the National Lottery. A common format is to relate some sort of tangential or episodic story and end by directly promoting the product or company of choice. Narratives tend to focus on everyday events that most families would be able to at least partially relate to. Many involve nuclear families and the day-to-day trials that they may go through. Common themes involve food, gender roles, entertainment, education, family, race and hygiene. Companies represented in the materials include GAMA, Philips, Procter & Gamble, Puig, and Unilever. Items in this collection appear in both Spanish and Catalan. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Arrangement
Items are numbered consecutively and housed by size.
Collection Overview
The aucas found in this collection span 1937-1985 and are focused primarily on advertising a range of products, businesses, services or entertainments such as films, but also present are public service announcements for topics such as safety, health or the National Lottery. A common format is to relate some sort of tangential or episodic story and end by directly promoting the product or company of choice. Narratives tend to focus on everyday events that most families would be able to at least partially relate to. Many involve nuclear families and the day-to-day trials that they may go through. Common themes involve food, gender roles, entertainment, education, family, race and hygiene. Companies represented in the materials include GAMA, Philips, Procter & Gamble, Puig, and Unilever. Items in this collection appear in both Spanish and Catalan. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Provenance
The Spanish Broadsides, Auca and Aleluya were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2013-2014
Historical note
The term "auca" refers to a paneled, cartoon-like graphic genre that originated in Catalonia in the 17th century. Some sources argue that the origin comes from the Latin "ave" in the sense of a sign or hailing, others that the term derives from a Catalan dialect word for "goose" which is the name of a game that still exists. Originally auca consisted only of images, possibly derived from playing cards or games of chance. The form evolved to comprise 24-48 panels (almost always in a multiple of four) with a rhymed couplet of text typically of seven syllables, although the poetic structure could vary. Mode of production evolved with available technology, from ink drawings to lithography to photography and modern printing methods.
During the 18th century, text and images tended to center around local fairs and festivals, anniversaries and other private and public events. By the mid-late 19th century the narrative served a more pedagogical function, and the genre came to be included in the ensemble of advertising literature. Also in the 19th century, the popularity of the Auca spread to Madrid and Castile, where it was known as "Aleluja" presumably linking the genre to the prevalence of religious tracts of the region.
Sources:
Tag Archives: Aleluya--Érase una vez: un "Auca"
Wikipedia: Auca (cartoon)
Advertising -- Spain; Advertising -- Spain -- 20th century; Broadsides (notices); John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Unilever (Firm); Philips; Procter & Gamble Company; Gama (Firm)
- Spanish, 1938-1985 and undated; 1
  - 1. Paraguas Alujes. Para Lo que Sirve El Paraguas--The Purpose of the Umbrella, Undated (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Summary of text: This auca details the many uses of the umbrella which include: making the user look presentable, providing shade, hiding from a debt collector, finding he who is in debt and many more. With a tone of humor, the auca ends by stating that the only situation in which the umbrella is not usable is during the rain.
  - 2. Viandox. Pulgarcito (El Ogro Satifecho)--Pulgarcito (The Satisfied Ogre), Undated (Box 1)
    Viandox is a seasoning/condiment produced by Unilever and marketed under the Knorr brand. Summary of text: Pulgarcito is a young boy who goes on an adventure and returns with the local orges boots and bag. Searching for another adventure, Pulgarcito goes back out and finds himself at the ogres house. The ogers wife then tells Pulgarcito that the ogre no longer eats children because, in order to save money, she has begun seasoning her food with VIANDOX. In the end, Pulgarcito returns to his mother with "the ultimate treasure: the secret to good cooking."
  - 3. Tex-Ton. El "Tex-ton" Salvador--The Savior "Tex-ton", 1943 (Box 1)
    Tex-Ton was a packaged goods producer. Summary of text: One day the hero, Canuto, awakes on a deserted island. He begins to scream in search of help when a "fierce black man" who "eats white men with rice" takes Canuto hostage. The black man feeds Canuto plenty in order to fatten him up and eventually eat him. One day, a box washes ashore containing TEX-TON SOUP. This soup was so tasty and filling that the tribe begins to celebrate and forgets about Canuto, giving him the chance to happily run away.
  - 4. Aleluyas de Panito--Aleluyas of Bread, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: This auca details the process of breadmaking beginning with the products used to make it and ending with the bread being sold at a bakery and eaten by a child. It ends stating that bread is the first natural nourishment and that when abundant in life, it reduces spending and brings happiness to one's life.
  - 5. Film: 75 Minutos de Angustia/The Man Who Cried Wolf. Una Historia sin Precendentes en los Anales Policiacos--A Story Without Precedents in Police Proceedings, 1939 (Box 1)
    American film starring Lewis Stone, Barbara Read and Tom Brown. Filmed in Universal City, California. Produced by Universal Studios. Released August 29, 1937 in USA. Released 17 June 1940 in Madrid. Directed by Lewis R. Foster. Summary of text: This auca is equivalent to what would now be considered a movie trailer. It is an advertisment for the 1937 film The Man Who Cried Wolf. It tells the story of a Lorenzo Fontaine, a muder that had been commited and the wrongful accusation of Fontaine's son. Fontaine, must now do what he can to prove his son's innocence before it is too late and his son is sent to the electric chair.
  - 6. Maxbel. La Historia de la Gastronomía puesta por MAXBEL--The history of gastronomy as told by MAXBEL, Undated (Box 1)
    Appliance manufacturer. Summary of text: An ad for a butane and regular gas MAXBEL stove, this auca beings by mentioning food from various countries including Greece, Italy and Russia. All the while, the owner of this stove has been cooking delicious food from these various countries using her "modern, simple yet marvelous" stove.
  - 7. Tip-Top. Esta historia verdadera, es la de un señor cualquiera--This true story could pertain to anyone, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: A man is constantly late for work because he fails to tie his shoe laces correctly, which leads to a series of mishaps and misfortunes. His boss is quite unhappy with him when one day the man discovers TIP-TOP, a elastic closing for one's shoes that eliminates the need for shoe laces. With this invention he is able to catch his train, be on time for work and make his boss happy.
  - 8. Airesan. Apuros de la familia KUSAN que el regresar de veraneo los soluciona con AIRESAN--The plight of the KUSAN family which, upon returning from their summer vacation, is resolved by AIRESAN, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: Airesan is a bug spray that helps a family out after they have returned from summer vaction to see that their house is infested with bug. This bug spray fights against cockroaches, fleas, mosquitoes, flies and many more insects.
  - 9. Tex-Ton. La Jornada de Doña Gertrudis--Miss Gertrudis' Journey, 1943 (Box 1)
    Tex-Ton was a packaged goods producer. Summary of text: Miss Gertrudis has a slew of errands to run. Between taking her kids to school, sweeping, making the beds and cleaning the house, she loses track of time and before she knows it her husband is home from work annd angry that there is no food on the table. In her quick thinking, Miss Gertrudis remembers TEX-TON soup and in five quick minutes the soup is ready and her husband is happy to have such a tasty meal.
  - 10. Yo periodical. La Revista de los Niños "yo" aparecerá el viernes día 4 Junio--The periodical/magazine of the children "I" will appear Friday, the June 4th, 1937 (Box 1)
    Summary of text: Two chldren ask their father for something amusing. While searching, the father finds a periodical that will keep the children entertained and that is full of emotion and stories. The periodical keeps the children so entertained that the mother has time to look for new recipes and cook enjoyable food. The periodical is available in millions.
  - 11. Divulgación popular del libro siempre libros baratos--Popuar release of book always cheap books, 1937 (Box 1)
    Local bookstore. Summary of text: The book store being advertised offers a wide array of literature that is sure to entertain any audience. From adventure-based children's books, to book about wars and revolutions to books so emotional that they could even make a lion cry, this book store carries everything and a visit will surely have you leaving happy.
  - 12. Agua del Carmen. Auca del Agua del Carmen--Auca of Carmen's water, 1968 (Box 1)
    Created in the 17th century. Formula is a concentration of medicinal plants. Product is still sold in pharmacies. Apparently, the main usage of this water was to prevent anxiety attacks or calm nerves. Supposed to be prescribed by a doctor. Summary of text: This water is advertised as being some of the best water possibly imaginable. It serves many, many purposes and can cure most illnesses. The advertisement warns agaisnt forgetting it when going on an important trip or eating dinner. Agua del Carmen can cure headaches, stomach aches and even insomnia. It is such a grand invention that it surely deserves a monument in the city.
  - 13. Film. Primavera en el Corazon: risa en imágenes graciosas, con bellas mujeres, bonitas canciones y muchas más cosas--Spring in the Heart: laugh with funny images, beautiful women, beautiful songs and many more things, 1957 (Box 1)
    Mexican film. Released September 26, 1956 in Mexico. Starring Andy Russel and Irasema Dilian. Directed by Roberto Rodriguez. Summary of text: This auca advertises a movie with what is supposed to be a humorous plot line. A couple finds themselves falling in love but later having issues when the woman in the relationship becomes jealous. She proposes marriage, in which the man is portrayed as literally being tied to a post with a rope. There is confusion and two brides show up to the wedding but in the end there is a happily ever after. This film is said to be sure to make the audience laugh and they will undoubtedly be back tomorrow to watch it again.
  - 14. CADETE book collection. El mejor regalo, el mejor CADETE--The best gift, the best toy: a book from the CADETE collection, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: A young boy is teased on the playground for not knowing who Dickens, Alcott or Walter Scott are. He goes home and asks his father for money to buy educational books from the CADETE collection. After reading these books the young boy is education about all things past and present. He is then portrayed as being the man in charge at his place of employment. In the end, the boy has become well-educated without concern of whether he was rich or poor because he was able to read CADETE.
  - 15. National lottery. Aleluyas de la lotería. Juegan el Blas y su tía--Aleluyas of the lottery. Blas and his aunt play, Undated (Box 1)
    Spanish lottery has been organized every year since 1812 and is organized by the Spanish Public Administration. This lottery is the second longest continuously running lottery in the world and is considered the biggest lottery in the world. Summary of text: Blas and his aunt have very good luck playing the lottery and start imagining all the things they could buy depending on the winning price of the gamble.
  - 16. Foundry of Salvador Manclus Andres. Lee con mucha atención, esta pagina que ves ¡Viva la Gran Fundicion, Salvador Manclus Andres!--Read this page that you see with much caution. !Long live the Grand Foundry, Salvador Manclus Andres!, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: When the bell at a local church stops working, the worried priest looks to Salvador Manclus Andres to fix it. Manclus does an extraordinary job at replacing the bell and the whole town is happy. Following that incident, the local clock breaks and Manclus comes to the rescue again, saving the day. His clocks and bells are of the highest quality and are sure to impress.
  - 17. National lottery. De como la lotería da optimismo y alegría--How the lottery gives optimism and hope, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: Pachin is a very poor man who just can't seem to make it. He struggles to make any money and it is implied that his girlfriend is a prostitute. One day he and his girlfriend sit and talk about what they wish their life would be. Pachin decides to buy a lottery ticket and ends up winning a lot of money. He and his girlfriend can now live a luxurious life and are able to give back to those who are also lower class. His girlfriend no longer has to prostitute herself and they now live a happy and prosperous life.
  - 18. CADETE book collection. El mejor regalo, el mejor CADETE--The best gift, the best toy: a book from the CADETE collection, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: A father is frustrated with his 12 year old daughter and 13 year old son. His daughter has become very superficial and his son has begun smoking cigarrettes. The father is unsure of what to do when he decides to purchase books from the CADETE collection for his children. The two then become very well-mannered and educated and the father is very proud to have been about to amend their ways. He is sure that the collection will reach at least 1000 volumes because it is so beneficial and useful.
  - 19. Escuela de Ingenieros Industriales de Barcelona. Auca de las Bodas de Plata de la Promoción 1933 Escuela de Ingenieros Industriales de Barcelona--Auca of the Weddings of Gold of the 1933 graduation from the Engineering Industrial school of Barcelona, 1958 (Box 1)
    The School of Industrial Engineering is part of the larger Universitat Politecnica de Catalunya (Technical University of Catalonia, UPC) and was created in 1851. This school is the biggest engineering school in Catalonia. Summary of text: Students at this school were able to learn about many, many different fields of study during their time at the school. There were courses on dance, mathematics, the sciences and so on. As the students graduated some obtained wealth while others didn't but in the end they were each able to find their field of study.
  - 20. Artilene. Relato en forma sencilla, de unas telas sin igual tesoro de maravilla--Story in simple form of some fabrics without the same treasure of marvel, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: Fabric was originially created by Adam and Eve when they couldn't find adequate clothing. The auca tells the story of the many styles and time periods that fabric has gone through since its creation. ARTILENE is a company that produces the finest fabrics possible, which do not crease, are easy to wash and store and generally make life less complicated. These fabrics are sure to be stupendous.
  - 21. Radio Barcelona. Vida de Radio Barcelona--Life of Radio Barcelona, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: Radio Barcelona provides any kind of entertainment or information one could want. It's weather announcements are helpful in preparing for the day. A religious station provides comfort for ones home and the cooking station allows one to learn new recipes. Along with the mentioned stations, the radio provides entertainment in the form of music, announcements and events.
  - 22. OKAL (medication). Contra el Dolor tableta OKAL--Anti-pain tablet OKAL, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: A wise religious leader opens a store where he sells seemingly majestical, white pills that are said to cure everything. Men, women and children visited his store with a variety of ailments looking to cure their suffering. With these pills, they never again experienced ailments and were very happy for the man and the OKAL pills. This auca is also translated into Arabic and French and seems to have references to Islam.
  - 23. Tío Nelo. Historia de Tío Nelo--The story of Uncle Nelo, Undated (Box 1)
    Tio Nelo is the name of a cafe specializing in horchata, a drink made from nuts, seeds and milk. Summary of text: Tio Nelo is a great cook and makes products that everyone loves. He eventually makes a lot of money off of his restaraunts and stops being as active as he once was. When he see that people are sad due to his absence he returns to cooking, which makes everyone very happy.
  - 24. Rover/Ebano. Pavimientos--Pavements, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: A couples home is in bad condition as the ceiling, walls and floor are due to be changed. The wife keeps telling her husband that it is time to update their house but their husband is very worried about the finances. He visits the ROVER/EBANO location and recieves a very low estimate for the cost of the materials. Luckily, he and his wife are able to update their house and can now enjoy their new ceiling, walls and floors thanks to ROVER/EBANO.
  - 25. Soldados GAMA. Juan y su amigo con sus soldados desmontables--Juan and his friend with their removable soldiers, Undated (Box 1)
    GAMA is a German toy company that has been around since before WW1. Summary of text: A young boy is showing his friend his GAMA toy soliders. As the boys play they create a scenario involving the toy soldiers and the toy Indians. The friend decides that he will ask the 3 magi for them as a gift.
  - 26. Film. "De pillo a pillo" se aclama por su lujo y por su trama--"From one scoundrel to another" is praised for its extravagance and drama, Undated (Box 1)
    Spanish film, a 1955 musical comedy by Adolfo Torrado and Daniel Montorio, starring Angel de Andres and Antonio Casal. Summary of text: This film follows 3 characters who start out as impoverished city dwellers but then encounter a fortune and begin to live a lavish lifestyle. They soon encounter issues and are forced to find a way to resolve them and live happily ever after.
  - 27. Marisa clase italiana helado (ice cream). En la Historia del Helado Marisa Fama ha Alcancazo--Marisa has reached fame in the story of the ice cream, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: Ice cream is enjoyed far and wide and Marisa brand ice cream only makes the experience more enjoyable. The whole world is now inclined to eat ice cream from this brand.
  - 28. NORIT laundry detergent. Aventuras de Jaimito o NORIT el borreguito--The Adventures of Jaimito or NORITO the little sheep, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: Jaimito is a very destructive young boy who is constantly breaking things and getting himself into trouble. One day his father becomes so angry at him that Jaimito gets grounded. Of course, Jaimito tries to hang from a shelf which he ends up knocking over and in the process dirties his close. His father becomes even angrier but his mother decides is that all she needs is a little NORIT to thoroughly clean the shirt.
  - 29. Werner pianos. Untitled, Undated (Box 1)
    Werner was established in Chicago in 1902. Summary of text: A neurotic man is constiently acting out and harming other people and himself. It is implied that one day he decided to take a broom for a ride (like a witch) but before going outside he sees an ad for a WERNER piano, which saves his life. He buys a piano and his neurosis is cured.
  - 30. Cel-lo tape. Untitled, Undated (Box 1)
    Name originated from "Sellotape", a British brand of transparent tape. Summary of text: The wise discovered CEL-LO tape and it was a life changing experience. It can be used to fix torn bills, torn books or for a variety of general uses. The whole world recognized that this tape is the best tape out there.
  - 31. Vermicidia Barcelo. Las Lombrices de Toto--Toto's Worms, Undated (Box 1)
    Vermicide, for intestinal parasites. Summary of text: Toto is a young boy who gets in trouble and is essentially put on a time out. During this time Toto comes across a cake and starts eating it. He somehow gets stomach worms from this cake and proceeds to become very ill. His father is looking for a remedy when he comes across Vermicidia Barcelo, which effectively cures him of his illness.
  - 32. Benet Campabadal. De Una Cinta Sin Igual: Aleluya de la cinta que ciñe adorna y precinta--Of a belt like no other: Aleluya of a belt that encirles, adorns and seals like no other, Undated (Box 1)
    Summary of text: Benet Campabal is a company that advertises making over 100,000 different kinds of belts and ribbon. This ad, details the many uses of the belt and ribbon throughout history. It mentions Adam and Eve, the Roman and Chinese empires and the "discovery" of America by Christopher Columbus. This last mention includes an image of what are assumed to be Native Americans bowing down to the colonists.
  - 33. Festival de la infancia--Children's Festival, 1964 (Box 1)
    Summary of text: The yearly children's festival is coming back to town and will be in Barcelona from Dec 19 1963 to Jan 5, 1964. This festival will include all the attractions a child could possibly want. There will be a ferris wheel, swings, an acrobat and many more. At one point there is a mention of "savages", one of who is portrayed as a native.
  - 34. Bomba Prat water pumps. Aleluya de la "Bomba Prat" o una solución verdad--Aleluya of "Bomba Prat"; or, a true solution, Undated (Box 1)